<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
	<channel>
		<title>Latest Science News -- ScienceDaily</title>
		<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/news/</link>
		<description></description>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 05:11:08 EST</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 05:11:08 EST</lastBuildDate>
		<ttl>60</ttl>
		<image>
			<title>Latest Science News -- ScienceDaily</title>
			<url>https://www.sciencedaily.com/images/scidaily-logo-rss.png</url>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/news/</link>
			<description>For more science news, visit ScienceDaily.</description>
		</image>
		<atom:link xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/rss/all.xml" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>This glowing particle in a laser trap may reveal how lightning begins</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124231904.htm</link>
			<description>Using a precisely aligned pair of laser beams, scientists can now hold a single aerosol particle in place and monitor how it charges up. The particle’s glow signals each step in its changing electrical state, revealing how electrons are kicked away and how the particle sometimes releases sudden bursts of charge. These behaviors mirror what may be happening inside storm clouds. The technique could help explain how lightning gets its initial spark.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 23:57:11 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124231904.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>This tiny plant survived the vacuum of space and still grows</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124231900.htm</link>
			<description>Moss spores survived an extended stay on the outside of the ISS and remained capable of germinating once back on Earth. Their resilience to vacuum, extreme temperatures, and UV radiation surprised the researchers who expected them to perish. The spores&#039; natural protective coat likely played a key role in shielding them. The study hints at the potential for simple plants to support agriculture beyond our planet.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 23:27:16 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124231900.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists find a hidden weak spot that may trigger Alzheimer’s</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094328.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have found that a mutation tied to Alzheimer’s disrupts the production and quality of exosomes—tiny cell-made communication packets. Cells with the defective SORLA protein generate fewer exosomes and ones far less able to support nearby brain cells. This weakness may be a key driver of Alzheimer’s development. The research points to new treatment strategies that enhance or restore exosome function.</description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 04:59:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094328.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Cocoa and tea may protect your heart from the hidden damage of sitting</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094325.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists found that high-flavanol foods can prevent the decline in blood vessel function that occurs after prolonged sitting. Even physically fit men weren’t protected unless they had consumed flavanols beforehand. A cocoa drink rich in these compounds kept arteries functioning normally. Everyday foods like berries, apples, tea, and certain cocoa products could offer a simple way to protect long-term vascular health.</description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:51:42 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094325.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists reveal a hidden alarm system inside your cells</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094323.htm</link>
			<description>Ribosomes don’t just make proteins—they can sense when something’s wrong. When they collide, they send out stress signals that activate a molecule called ZAK. Researchers uncovered how ZAK recognizes these collisions and turns them into protective responses. The discovery shows how cells quickly spot trouble.</description>
			<pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 03:17:57 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094323.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Europe launches bold plan to harness twisting beams of light</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094319.htm</link>
			<description>Europe is investing in a coordinated effort to develop high-power optical vortex technologies and train new specialists in the field. The HiPOVor network unites academia and industry to advance applications ranging from material processing to environmentally friendly photonic systems.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:46:24 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094319.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Vegan diet beats Mediterranean for weight loss even with potatoes and grains</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094317.htm</link>
			<description>Participants lost more weight on a low-fat vegan diet than on the Mediterranean diet, largely due to eliminating animal foods and reducing oils and nuts. Increased intake of plant foods, even “unhealthy” ones, was strongly associated with greater weight loss.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:03:07 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094317.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists find hidden switch that lets tumors shapeshift and evade treatment</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094314.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists are uncovering what makes some carcinomas so resistant: their ability to change identity. Two new studies reveal crucial proteins and structures that could become targets for future therapies. These discoveries deepen understanding of how tumors reprogram themselves and point toward highly specific treatments. The work raises hopes for safer, more selective cancer drugs.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 10:26:21 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124094314.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Immune cells use a surprising trick to heal muscle faster</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124075330.htm</link>
			<description>A research team has found that specific immune cells can connect with muscle fibers in a lightning-fast, neuron-like way to promote healing. These cells deliver quick pulses of calcium, triggering repair within seconds. The mechanism works in both injury and disease models. The discovery could inspire new treatments for muscle recovery and degeneration.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 08:06:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124075330.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Global surge in ultra-processed foods sparks urgent health warning</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124025654.htm</link>
			<description>Ultra-processed foods are rapidly becoming a global dietary staple, and new research links them to worsening health outcomes around the world. Scientists say only bold, coordinated policy action can counter corporate influence and shift food systems toward healthier options.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 03:07:46 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251124025654.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New obesity discovery rewrites decades of fat metabolism science</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115712.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have uncovered a surprising new role for the HSL protein: beyond breaking down fat, it also works inside the nucleus of fat cells to keep them functioning properly. When HSL is missing, fat tissue doesn’t expand as expected— instead, it shrinks, leading to lipodystrophy. This unexpected discovery helps explain why both obesity and fat-loss disorders share similar health risks, and it opens up fresh paths for understanding metabolic diseases at a time when obesity affects billions worldwide.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:19:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115712.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Your brain shows damage before your blood pressure even rises</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115708.htm</link>
			<description>Hypertension begins harming the brain surprisingly early, even before measurable blood pressure increases. Key cells related to blood vessels, signaling, and myelin maintenance begin aging prematurely and malfunctioning. These disruptions resemble early patterns seen in cognitive decline and Alzheimer’s. Encouragingly, losartan reversed some of this early damage in mice.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 09:33:36 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115708.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>One protein may hold the key to fixing leukemia treatment failure</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115703.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have uncovered how leukemia cells manage to escape one of the most commonly used treatments. Over time, these cancer cells subtly change the shape of their mitochondria to avoid dying when the drug tries to kill them. By identifying the protein that controls this shape-shifting, researchers were able to block it in mice, making the treatment powerful again and dramatically extending survival.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:57:03 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115703.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A mysterious metal find in Sweden is rewriting Iron Age history</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115658.htm</link>
			<description>A Swedish plano-convex ingot once thought to be from the Bronze Age was revealed through chemical and isotopic testing to belong to the Iron Age. Its composition closely matches Iron Age finds from Poland, leading researchers to uncover new evidence of long-distance connections across the Baltic. The study highlights how collaboration and scientific analysis can transform isolated artifacts into clues about ancient trade and networking.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 14:57:15 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115658.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Record sargassum piles trap sea turtle hatchlings on Florida beaches</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115439.htm</link>
			<description>Sargassum seaweed is creating major new obstacles for sea turtle hatchlings, drastically slowing their crawl to the ocean and increasing their risk from predators and heat. Despite the physical challenge, their energy stores stay stable, suggesting the real danger lies in the delay itself.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 06:37:28 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115439.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>What 96,000 adults taught scientists about preventing constipation</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115437.htm</link>
			<description>A massive long-term study shows that Mediterranean and plant-based diets can help prevent chronic constipation in aging adults. Surprisingly, the benefits weren’t explained by fiber alone. Western and inflammatory diets raised constipation risk, while low-carb diets showed minimal impact. The research underscores how diet quality influences gut health well beyond traditional advice.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:26:37 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115437.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>CRISPR wheat that makes its own fertilizer</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115435.htm</link>
			<description>UC Davis researchers engineered wheat that encourages soil bacteria to convert atmospheric nitrogen into plant-usable fertilizer. By boosting a natural compound in the plant, the wheat triggers bacteria to form biofilms that enable nitrogen fixation. This breakthrough could cut fertilizer use, reduce pollution, and increase yields. It also offers huge potential savings for farmers worldwide.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:00:24 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115435.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>How parakeets make new friends in a surprisingly human way</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115434.htm</link>
			<description>Monk parakeets ease into new friendships, slowly approaching strangers to avoid aggressive encounters. Researchers watched how birds shared space, groomed each other, and escalated to deeper social bonds over time. The results show a clear pattern of cautious exploration echoing similar studies in other animals. Even for birds, making a friend can be a delicate dance.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 14:23:18 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115434.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists may have found the planet that made the Moon</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115431.htm</link>
			<description>About 4.5 billion years ago, a colossal impact between the young Earth and a mysterious planetary body called Theia changed everything—reshaping Earth, forming the Moon, and scattering clues across space rocks. By examining subtle isotopic fingerprints in Earth and Moon samples, scientists have reconstructed Theia’s possible composition and birthplace.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 13:03:07 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123115431.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A tiny enzyme may hold the key to safer pain relief</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085557.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have uncovered a surprising way the brain switches pain on, revealing that neurons can release an enzyme outside the cell that activates pain signals without disrupting normal movement or sensation. This enzyme, called VLK, modifies nearby proteins in a way that intensifies pain and strengthens connections tied to learning and memory. Removing VLK in mice dramatically reduced post-surgery pain while leaving normal function untouched, offering a promising path toward safer, more targeted pain treatments.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:33:03 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085557.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists capture stunning real-time images of DNA damage and repair</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085554.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have created a live-cell DNA sensor that reveals how damage appears and disappears inside living cells, capturing the entire repair sequence as it unfolds. Instead of freezing cells at different points, researchers can now watch damage flare up, track repair proteins rushing to the site, and see the moment the DNA is restored. Built from a natural protein that binds gently and briefly to damaged DNA, the sensor offers a true-to-life view of the cell’s internal emergency response.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 09:52:27 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085554.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Boosting one protein helps the brain protect itself from Alzheimer’s</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085550.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers discovered that raising the protein Sox9 can help the brain’s astrocytes clear out toxic plaque buildup linked to Alzheimer’s. In mouse models that already showed memory problems, activating these cells improved cognitive performance. The treatment also reduced plaque levels over time. The work points toward a natural, cell-based way to slow Alzheimer’s decline.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 09:23:57 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251123085550.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Solar Superstorm Gannon crushed Earth’s plasmasphere to a record low</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122234723.htm</link>
			<description>A massive solar storm in May 2024 gave scientists an unprecedented look at how Earth’s protective plasma layer collapses under intense space weather. With the Arase satellite in a perfect observing position, researchers watched the plasmasphere shrink to a fraction of its usual size and take days to rebuild. The event pushed auroras far beyond their normal boundaries and revealed that a rare “negative storm” in the ionosphere dramatically slowed the atmosphere’s ability to recover. These observations offer valuable insight into how extreme solar activity disrupts satellites, GPS signals, and communication systems.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:00:14 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122234723.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists reveal how baby turtles navigate thousands of miles with a hidden magnetic sense</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122225829.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers taught young loggerhead turtles to associate certain magnetic fields with feeding, prompting a distinctive dance when they recognized the signal. After a magnetic pulse briefly disrupted their ability to feel magnetic forces, the turtles no longer performed the dance. This showed that hatchlings use a touch-based magnetic sense to determine their location. The discovery clarifies how these animals find their way across vast ocean routes.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 22:58:29 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122225829.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scholars say most of what we believe about Vikings is wrong</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044340.htm</link>
			<description>Ideas about Vikings and Norse mythology come mostly from much later medieval sources, leaving plenty of room for reinterpretation. Over centuries, writers, politicians, and artists reshaped these stories to reflect their own worldviews, from romantic heroism to dangerous nationalist myths. Pop culture and neo-paganism continue to amplify selective versions of this past. Scholars today are unraveling how these shifting visions emerged and how they influence identity and culture.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 03:34:17 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044340.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Nearby super-Earth emerges as a top target in the search for life</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044338.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have pinpointed a super-Earth in the habitable zone of a nearby M-dwarf star only 18 light-years away. Sophisticated instruments detected the planet’s gentle tug on its star, hinting at a rocky world that could hold liquid water. Future mega-telescopes may be able to directly image it—something impossible today.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 01:38:58 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044338.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hidden high-energy water reveals a new molecular force</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044336.htm</link>
			<description>Water trapped inside tiny molecular cavities behaves in a surprisingly energetic way, pushing outward like people crammed in an elevator. When a new molecule enters these narrow spaces, the confined water forces its way out—boosting the strength of the molecular bond that forms in its place. Researchers from KIT and Constructor University have now proven this effect both experimentally and theoretically, showing that these &quot;highly energetic&quot; water molecules can dramatically influence how other molecules interact.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 04:43:36 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044336.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hidden microglia switch helps protect the brain from Alzheimer’s</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044335.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists discovered that lowering a specific molecule helps microglia switch into a protective state that quiets brain inflammation in Alzheimer’s. A small group of these cells seems to have an outsized ability to keep the brain healthier. When a key signal is removed from them, Alzheimer’s symptoms worsen. This pathway may help explain why some people naturally have reduced Alzheimer’s risk.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 13:02:52 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044335.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The surprising reason bees replace their queens</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044333.htm</link>
			<description>Worker bees stage coordinated revolts when viral infections weaken their queen and lower her pheromone output. This disruption drives many of the queen failures that beekeepers struggle with today. Field trials show that synthetic pheromone blends can prevent untimely supersedure, opening a path to more stable hive management.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 11:56:18 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044333.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A high-altitude telescope just changed what we know about black holes</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044331.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists flew the XL-Calibur telescope on a high-altitude balloon to measure polarized X-rays from Cygnus X-1. These measurements reveal details about the chaotic, superheated material swirling around black holes. The team also captured data from the Crab pulsar and achieved multiple technical breakthroughs during the 2024 mission. Another flight from Antarctica is expected to expand this cosmic investigation.</description>
			<pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 02:16:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044331.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New nasal nanodrops wipe out brain tumors in mice</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044329.htm</link>
			<description>A new nasal-delivered nanotherapy shows promise against aggressive glioblastoma tumors. By activating the STING immune pathway using gold-core spherical nucleic acids, researchers were able to reach the brain without invasive surgery. When paired with drugs that boost T-cell activity, the treatment eliminated tumors in mice and built long-lasting immunity. The results suggest a powerful new direction for brain cancer immunotherapy.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 12:24:13 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044329.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>AI detects a secret lion roar no one knew existed</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044327.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have uncovered a surprising second type of lion roar, using AI to decode vocal signatures with remarkable precision. This breakthrough sheds new light on how lions communicate and offers a powerful new tool for conservationists racing to protect shrinking populations.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 11:29:08 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044327.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Hidden copper switch supercharges green ammonia production</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044325.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers discovered that copper oxide catalysts form metallic copper mid-reaction, triggering a dramatic boost in ammonia output. The insight offers a roadmap for designing cleaner, more efficient ammonia-production technologies.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 10:48:23 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044325.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Fossils reveal a massive shark that ruled Australia in dinosaur times</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044321.htm</link>
			<description>Around 115 million years ago, northern Australia’s seas hosted a colossal shark that rewrites what we thought we knew about early ocean predators. New fossil discoveries show that modern-type sharks were experimenting with gigantic sizes far earlier than scientists believed, competing with the marine “monsters” of the dinosaur age.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 05:08:49 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122044321.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Rapid fault healing could rewrite earthquake physics</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122020204.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists discovered that deep earthquake faults can heal far faster than expected, sometimes within hours. Slow slip events in Cascadia reveal repeated fault movements that only make sense if the fault quickly regains strength. Lab experiments show that mineral grains can weld together under intense heat and pressure, acting like a natural glue. This rapid cohesion may be a missing factor in earthquake modeling.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 02:37:56 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122020204.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Just a few cigarettes a day can damage your heart for decades</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122000802.htm</link>
			<description>People who smoke only a couple of cigarettes a day still face surprisingly high risks of heart problems and early death. A large review of long-term studies shows that even very light smokers can see their risk of heart failure climb sharply. While quitting leads to major health improvements, some risk remains for decades. The safest approach is quitting entirely, especially at younger ages.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:19:55 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251122000802.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why did ancient people build massive, mysterious mounds in Louisiana?</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090744.htm</link>
			<description>Hunter-gatherers at Poverty Point may have built its massive earthworks not under the command of chiefs, but as part of a vast, temporary gathering of egalitarian communities seeking spiritual harmony in a volatile world. New radiocarbon data and reexamined artifacts suggest far-flung travelers met to trade, worship, and participate in rituals designed to appease the forces of nature.</description>
			<pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 13:14:54 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090744.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New evidence shows tirzepatide and semaglutide strongly protect the heart</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090742.htm</link>
			<description>A massive real-world study comparing tirzepatide and semaglutide reveals both drugs deliver strong, early cardiovascular protection—reducing heart attack, stroke, and death in adults with type 2 diabetes. While companies have claimed large differences favoring their own medications, researchers found only modest distinctions between the two blockbuster GLP-1 drugs.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 23:10:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090742.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists reveal a hidden hormone switch for learning</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090740.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers uncovered how estrogen subtly reshapes learning by strengthening dopamine reward signals in the brain. Rats learned faster when estrogen levels were high and struggled when the hormone’s activity was blocked. The findings help explain how hormonal cycles influence cognitive performance and psychiatric symptoms. This connection offers a new path for understanding brain disorders tied to dopamine.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 23:32:51 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090740.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Our Solar System is racing through space 3x faster than we thought</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090738.htm</link>
			<description>New measurements of radio galaxies reveal that the solar system is racing through the universe at over three times the speed predicted by standard cosmology. Using highly sensitive data from multiple radio telescope arrays, researchers uncovered a surprisingly strong dipole pattern—one that challenges longstanding assumptions about how matter is distributed across cosmic scales. The results echo similar anomalies seen in quasar studies, hinting that something fundamental about our universe’s structure or our motion through it may need rewriting.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 09:29:25 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090738.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Stem cell therapy helps AMD patients see again</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090736.htm</link>
			<description>A first-of-its-kind trial is testing adult stem cell transplants for advanced dry macular degeneration. Early results show the treatment is safe and can significantly improve vision, even in severely affected patients. Participants gained measurable sight improvements in the treated eye. Researchers are now monitoring higher-dose groups as the therapy advances toward later trial phases.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 08:46:07 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090736.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The five great forests that keep North America’s birds alive</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090735.htm</link>
			<description>Migratory birds that fill North American forests with spring songs depend on Central America’s Five Great Forests far more than most people realize. New research shows these tropical strongholds shelter enormous shares of species like Wood Thrushes, Cerulean Warblers, and Golden-winged Warblers—many of which are rapidly declining. Yet these forests are disappearing at an alarming pace due to illegal cattle ranching, placing both birds and local communities at risk.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 08:35:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090735.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>The mystery of volcanoes that don’t explode finally has an answer</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090733.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have uncovered a long-missing piece of the volcanic puzzle: rising magma doesn’t just form explosive gas bubbles when pressure drops—it can do so simply by being sheared and “kneaded” inside a volcano’s conduit. These shear forces can trigger early bubble growth, create escape channels for gas, and sometimes turn potentially catastrophic magmas into surprisingly gentle lava flows.</description>
			<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 02:00:59 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090733.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Simple amino acid supplement greatly reduces Alzheimer’s damage</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090731.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers discovered that the common amino acid arginine can block harmful Aβ aggregation and reduce its toxic effects in Alzheimer’s disease models. In flies and mice, oral arginine lowered plaque levels, reduced inflammation, and improved behavior. Its strong safety record and low cost make it a promising repurposing candidate. The findings hint at a surprisingly simple path toward more accessible AD therapies.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 11:33:04 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090731.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A drug already in trials may stop chemotherapy nerve damage</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090729.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers discovered that chemotherapy can accidentally trigger a stress alarm in immune cells, causing inflammation that damages nerves. Blocking this alarm protected mice from nerve pain and kept their nerves healthier. A drug already being tested for cancer may help do the same in people. Early blood tests suggest it may even be possible to predict who will develop these symptoms before they happen.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 11:02:54 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090729.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New airflow device captures indoor germs before they spread</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090726.htm</link>
			<description>A new airflow device from UBC Okanagan engineers traps exhaled aerosols almost immediately, sharply reducing pathogen exposure in indoor spaces. Early simulations suggest it could outperform existing ventilation systems by a wide margin.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 10:08:14 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121090726.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists reveal kissing began millions of years before humans</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082053.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have traced kissing back to early primates, suggesting it began long before humans evolved. Their analysis points to great apes and even Neanderthals sharing forms of kissing millions of years ago. The behavior appears to have persisted through evolution as a social or bonding tool. Yet its patchy presence across human cultures hints at a mix of biology and cultural invention.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 09:35:13 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082053.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>This engineered fungus cuts emissions and tastes like meat</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082049.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists used CRISPR to boost the efficiency and digestibility of a fungus already known for its meatlike qualities. The modified strain grows protein far more quickly and with much less sugar while producing substantially fewer emissions. It also outperforms chicken farming in land use and water impact.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:57:41 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082049.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>This tiny pill could change how we diagnose gut health</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082046.htm</link>
			<description>Tiny ingestible spheres filled with engineered bacteria can detect intestinal bleeding by glowing when they encounter heme. Early tests in mice suggest they could become a quick, noninvasive way to monitor gut disease.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:30:39 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251121082046.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Why saving microbes may be the most important conservation effort ever</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120102600.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have launched the first coordinated plan to protect microbial biodiversity, calling attention to the “invisible 99% of life” that drives essential Earth systems. The IUCN has formally recognized this effort through the creation of the Microbial Conservation Specialist Group. By developing new metrics, policies, and restoration tools, scientists aim to make microbial life a core part of global conservation action. The roadmap also outlines upcoming goals such as microbial hotspot maps and new microbe-based conservation solutions.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:49:56 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120102600.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists grow a tiny human “blood factory” that actually works</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120092103.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have recreated a miniature human bone marrow system that mirrors the real structure found inside our bones. The model includes the full mix of cells and signals needed for blood production and even maintains this process for weeks. It could transform how scientists study blood cancers and test new drugs. In the future, it may support more personalized treatment strategies.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:24:49 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120092103.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Light has been hiding a magnetic secret for nearly 200 years</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120091945.htm</link>
			<description>New research shows that light’s magnetic field is far more influential than scientists once believed. The team found that this magnetic component significantly affects how light rotates as it passes through certain materials. Their work challenges a 180-year-old understanding of the Faraday Effect and opens pathways to new optical and magnetic technologies.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 09:59:00 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120091945.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A compact fusion machine just hit gigapascal pressures</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002836.htm</link>
			<description>Operating a new device named the Fusion Z-pinch Experiment 3, or FuZE-3, Zap Energy has now achieved plasmas with electron pressures as high as 830 megapascals (MPa), or 1.6 gigapascals (GPa) total, comparable to the pressures found deep below Earth’s crust.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:28:36 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002836.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>MIT ultrasonic tech pulls drinking water from air in minutes</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002834.htm</link>
			<description>MIT engineers have created an ultrasonic device that rapidly frees water from materials designed to absorb moisture from the air. Instead of waiting hours for heat to evaporate the trapped water, the system uses high-frequency vibrations to release droplets in just minutes. It can be powered by a small solar cell and programmed to cycle continuously throughout the day. The breakthrough could help communities with limited access to fresh water.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 02:33:18 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002834.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New report reveals major risks in turning oceans into carbon sinks</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002832.htm</link>
			<description>Experts say the ocean could help absorb carbon dioxide, but today’s technologies are too uncertain to be scaled up safely. New findings released during COP30 highlight the risks of rushing into marine carbon removal without proper monitoring and verification. With the 1.5°C threshold approaching, researchers stress that emissions cuts must remain the top priority. Ocean-based methods may play a role later, but they need careful oversight first.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 01:52:08 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002832.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Scientists reawaken exhausted T cells to supercharge cancer immunity</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002828.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers discovered a way to keep T cells from wearing out during the fight against cancer, and the approach could make immune-based treatments far more powerful. They found that tumors use a particular molecular signal to weaken T cells, and that interrupting this signal helps the cells stay active.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:28:28 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002828.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Japanese spacecraft faces a massive challenge from a house-size asteroid</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002619.htm</link>
			<description>New observations show that asteroid 1998 KY26 is a mere 11 meters across and spinning twice as fast as previously thought. The discovery adds complexity to Hayabusa2’s 2031 mission but also heightens scientific interest. The asteroid’s composition remains uncertain, making the encounter even more compelling. Insights from this work could improve future asteroid-defense and exploration efforts.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 04:19:58 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002619.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Century-old catalysis puzzle cracked by measuring a fraction of an electron</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002617.htm</link>
			<description>Scientists have directly measured the minuscule electron sharing that makes precious-metal catalysts so effective. Their new technique, IET, reveals how molecules bind and react on metal surfaces with unprecedented clarity. The insights promise faster discovery of advanced catalysts for energy, chemicals, and manufacturing.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 03:39:39 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002617.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>A twist of light could power the next generation of memory devices</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002614.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers have discovered a way to store information using a rare class of materials called ferroaxials, which rely on swirling electric dipoles instead of magnetism or charge. These vortex-like states are naturally stable and resistant to outside interference, but until now were almost impossible to control. By using circularly polarized terahertz light, scientists were able to flip these tiny rotational patterns on command, opening the door to a new form of robust, ultrafast, and long-lasting data storage.</description>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 03:17:47 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002614.htm</guid>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>New research shows hot tubs trigger surprising health benefits saunas don’t</title>
			<link>https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002611.htm</link>
			<description>Researchers found that hot tubs raise core body temperature more effectively than traditional or infrared saunas, leading to stronger boosts in blood flow and immune activity. Only hot-water immersion produced measurable changes in inflammatory markers. These effects can persist beyond the session, suggesting a sustained health benefit. For anyone unable or unwilling to exercise, heat therapy may offer a surprisingly effective option.</description>
			<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:26:11 EST</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2025/11/251120002611.htm</guid>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
<!-- cached Tue, 25 Nov 2025 05:11:05 EST -->